Inventory of the Lydia Bubeshko Schmüser papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Lydia Bubeshko Schmüser papers
1944-1994
2003C74
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Diary and correspondence, relating to social conditions in China during and after World War II. Includes letters written by Carl Otto Hans Schmüser, German citizen and husband of Lydia Schmüser. Also includes form letters and printed ephemera relating to postwar American politics.
Schmüser, Lydia Bubeshko, d. 2002
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2003.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Lydia Bubeshko Schmüser, an American of Russian descent, lived in China with her husband, German citizen, Carl Otto Hans Schmüser, and their daughter before and during World War II. The family owned and operated a paper and stationary shop in Tientsin, which they sold shortly after the outbreak of World War II. During World War II and the Japanese occupation of China, the family fled to the relative quiet of Bedaihe (Peitaiho), a village in northern China, where they owned a summer cottage. After the war, Schmüser and her daughter immigrated to the United States, settling in Los Angeles in 1947. Carl Otto Hans Schmüser was unable to join them, due to the restrictive immigration laws of the time. In 1952, the Senate passed a special relief bill authorizing a visa for Schmüser however he died on the very same day and was never reunited with his wife and daughter.
Scope and Content of Collection
Diary and correspondence, relating to social conditions in China during and after World War II. Includes letters written by Carl Otto Hans Schmüser, German citizen and husband of Lydia Schmüser. Also includes form letters and printed ephemera relating to postwar American politics.
Schmüser, Carl Otto Hans, dd. 1952.; Americans--China.; China--Social conditions.; Germans--China.; World War, 1939-1945--China.
- Writings, 1944-1974, undated
  - Diary, handwritten copy, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Notes, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Diary "Introduction," draft, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Diary "Fair Copy", undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - "Little Pictures of China in the Year 1944," draft (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - "Wartime Diary of Lydia Bubeshko Schmüser, Los Angeles, California", 1974 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Correspondence, 1947-1994
  - Hans Schmüser Correspondence, 1947-1952
    - April 1947-May 1949, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - May 1949-May 1952, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Political Correspondence, 1969-1994
    - Pamphlets and ephemera, 1969-1982 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Democratic Members of Congress correspondence, 1969-1982 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - General political correspondence and ephemera, 1978-1989 (Box-folder 2: 3, Box-folder 3: 1-2)
    - Republican National Committee correspondence, 1977-1994 (Box-folder 2: 4-6)